<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon on the occasion of the death of Algernon Sidney, Esq. Who was beheaded on Tower-Hill, on December the seventh 1683. for high-treason</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2539A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826755</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826755</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1829:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon on the occasion of the death of Algernon Sidney, Esq. Who was beheaded on Tower-Hill, on December the seventh 1683. for high-treason</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for J. Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sidney, Algernon, 1622-1683.</term>
               <term>Treason --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FUNERAL SERMON ON THE OCCASION OF THE DEATH OF <hi>Algernon Sidney,</hi> Eſq.</p>
            <p>Who was <hi>BEHEADED</hi> on <hi>TOWER-HILL,</hi> on <hi>December</hi> the ſeventh 1683. for <hi>HIGH-TREASON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Smith.</hi> M DC LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:31161:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31161:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Numbers XVI. 1, 2, 3, 4.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now</hi> Korah <hi>the Son of</hi> Izhar, <hi>the Son of</hi> Kohath, <hi>the Son of</hi> Levi <hi>and</hi> Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram <hi>the Sons of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liab, <hi>and</hi> On <hi>the Son of</hi> Peleth; <hi>Sons of</hi> Reuben, <hi>took Men,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they roſe up before</hi> Moſes, <hi>with certain of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Two Hundred and Fifty Princes of the Aſſembly, Fathers in the Congregation, Men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they gathered themſelves together againſt</hi> Moſes, <hi>and against</hi> Aaron, <hi>and ſaid unto them, Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation are Holy, every one of them, and the Lord is among them; wherefore then lift you up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And when</hi> Moſes <hi>heard it, he fell upon his Face,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:31161:3"/>
            <p> SUCH is Satan's Malice, and the Corruption of Man's Nature, That the Church of God is Exerciſed with variety of Difficulties and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions; <hi>Satan</hi> turning himſelf into divers ſhapes, appearing in variety of Forms, and by ſeveral ſorts of Inſtruments; ſometimes acting one part, and ſometimes another, whereof we have plentiful E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences in the Hiſtory of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> penned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who wrote the Story of many hundred years, and in the Book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and this Book of <hi>Numbers,</hi> the things that befel (for the moſt part) his own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Satan</hi> ſeemed to ſhew himſelf in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> like a roaring Lyon, or a wild Boar of the Forreſt, breaking into the Vineyard of the Lord of Hoſts, commanding firſt the Midwives, and afterwards his own People, to caſt every Son of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſhould be born, into the <hi>River Nilus, Exod.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. the laſt. And withal made the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> themſelves to ſerve with rigour, and to ſigh for hard Bondage.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31161:3"/>2. And when (as it appeareth) after <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were ſent from the Lord to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and the Lord ſealed to it by many Miracles, the Devil appeared in the ſhape of a Mountebank or Jugler; apiſhly imitating the glorious Works of God by counterfeit Signs, and Lying Wonders, until the Lord did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found him, and brought him to an open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>This is the Finger of God.</hi> Afterward he proceedeth no further that way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now in the third place, the Devil puts on his Harneſs, and appears like a mighty man ſtirring up <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by force of Arms to deſtroy them, and bring them back again into Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage after they marched out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but the Lord cauſed the Sea to fwallow up <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And now Satan remembring, how he prevailed over our firſt Parents in the Form of a Serpent, he putteth on that ſhape, and windeth into the Boſoms of many of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> ſtiring them up to Pride, Murmuring,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31161:4"/> Idolatry, Fornication, Tempting of God, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and at laſt to Unbelief and Apoſtacy; hereupon the Lord paſſeth Sentence upon them, and excludeth them out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land, and adjudging them to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Forty years in the Wilderneſs, the Lord reſerved the Mercies they had forfeited, for their innocent Children.</p>
            <p>Now in this time of Vacation, their old E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy was not idle, bnt ſeems to take upon him the appearance of an Angel of Light, and by his Accomplices ſets on foot the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling Deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Factors, <hi>Corah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> who ſaid unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Ye take too much upon you.</hi> What need have we of Prince and Prieſt, ſeeing all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation are Holy, every one of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was a moſt miſchievous Plot, and more like to undermine the Church than <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Rage and Cruelty.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:31161:4"/>
            <p>Where ye may obſerve two things; Firſt the Mutineers Attempt, and in that Four Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Actors,</hi> and they are of two ranks.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Principals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Acceſſories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Principals</hi> are deſcribed by their Names and Pedigree.</p>
            <p>And of theſe there were <hi>Two Parties. Korah a Levite,</hi> and <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram Reubenites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Korah</hi> and his Pedigree: He was deſcended of <hi>Levi,</hi> of the ſame Tribe whereof <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> was; yea he was of the principal Family of <hi>Levi,</hi> coming from <hi>Kohath,</hi> who was the principal Son of <hi>Levi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is thought to be one cauſe of the diſcontent, becauſe the preheminence was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Elizapban</hi> the Son of <hi>Uzziel, Numb.</hi> 3. 30. He was appointed to be the Chief of the Houſe of the Family of the <hi>Kahathites. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaphan</hi> was of the Fourth and youngeſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Kahathites,</hi> yet preferred to be Prince over them. This (as the <hi>Hebrews</hi> think) was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31161:5"/> offenſive to <hi>Korah,</hi> who was of the ſecond Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Izhar,</hi> and occaſioned him to rebel. <hi>Korah</hi> is noted as the Principal in the Rebellion, which St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls the <hi>Gainſaying of Kore.</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Jude, v.</hi> the 11. And in <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. 3. on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Korah</hi>'s Companies are mentioned, where Speech is of this mutiny. To <hi>Elizaphan</hi> was given the charge of the Ark and the Table, and the Candleſtick and the Altars, and the Veſſels of the Sanctuary, wherewith they miniſter, and the hangings, and all the ſervice thereof; therefore (as <hi>R. Sol. Jarchi</hi> on <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. noteth) <hi>Korah</hi> was offended, that <hi>Elizaphan</hi> and his Family ſhould <hi>have this Honourable Charge</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Korah</hi> and his Poſterity. Another part of theſe Actors were <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and <hi>On,</hi> Sons of <hi>Reuben (i. e.)</hi> deſcended from <hi>Reuben,</hi> who had forfeited his Birth-right by defiling his Fathers Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reuben</hi> had loſt his Honour by his Sin; which his Sons by unlawful means ſeek to recover.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:31161:5"/>
            <p>By the Sequel it appeareth, that <hi>Korah</hi> lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up himſelf, not only againſt <hi>Elizaphan;</hi> but againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of <hi>Levi,</hi> the Third Son of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and they did not only ſtomach at the perſonal preferment of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but ſought the Prieſthood alſo, <hi>verſe</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Now compare their Stations, <hi>Numb.</hi> 2. 10. Ye ſhall find, that the <hi>Reubenites</hi> were to be placed on the South-ſide of the Camp of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;</hi> and on the otherſide the <hi>Kohathites,</hi> of whom <hi>Korah</hi> was, encamped on the ſide of the Tabernacle South ward, <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 29. Theſe <hi>Reubenites</hi> encamped next unto the <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hathites,</hi> and ſo being Neighbours in Situati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aſſociated themſelves in evil, which <hi>Sol. Jarchi</hi> obſerving, ſaith, <hi>woe, be unto the wicked, and woe unto his Neighbour.</hi> Their quarters being ſo near one to another, their Agitators had leave to confer together, and to hatch this Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Acceſſories</hi> in general were certain of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31161:6"/> the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> In particular <hi>Two Hundred and Fifty Men,</hi> deſcribed firſt by their Degree, Princes of the Aſſembly, or <hi>Called</hi> of the Aſſembly, or <hi>Senatours</hi> called to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, Men of Name, of Renown, famous in the Congregation, whereby the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was the ſtronger. A ſmall number in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thoſe, who were under <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; yet in regard of their Eminence, ſuch as had a great Influence upon the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider their Deſign, which as it was cloſely carried by them, ſo it is covertly laid down here. Their Aim was to deſtroy the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government ſetled by God in the Church and Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> to degrade <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> from their Dignities, and in Caſe of reſiſtance to murther them, and to raiſe themſelves to the Chief Places of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and ſo to bring the People into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Slavery, of whoſe Liberty they ſeemed ſo zealous.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:31161:6"/>1. That their Aim was at the Prieſthood, it appeareth by <hi>Moſes</hi> his upbrading them, <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. And <hi>Moſes ſaid unto</hi> Korah; <hi>Hear I pray you, ye Sons of</hi> Levi, <hi>ſeemeth it but a ſmall thing to you, that the God of Iſrael hath ſeperated you from the Congregation of Iſrael; to bring you near unto himſelf, to do the Service of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the Congregation, to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto them? And he hath brought thee near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and all thy Brethren the Sons of Levi with you, and ſeek ye the Prieſthood alſo?</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>For which Cauſe, both thou, and all thy Company are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together againſt the Lord: And what is Aaron, that ye murmur againſt him?</hi> As if he had ſaid, is it not enough, that God hath advanced you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thouſands of your Brethren, but that ye will lift up your ſelves above <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſeek the Prieſthood alſo? This was the deſign or the <hi>Kahathites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the deſign of the <hi>Reube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> was againſt the Scepter, <hi>verſe</hi> 12, 13. and <hi>Moſes</hi> ſent to call <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> the Son of <hi>Eliab,</hi> which ſaid, <hi>we will not come up;</hi> that is,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31161:7"/> we will not come up unto the publick place of Judgment, where <hi>Moſes</hi> by debateing with them, might had perſwaded them to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted from their evil enterprize, and have found mercy. <hi>Is it a ſmall thing</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>that thou haſt brought us up out of a Land that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Milk and Honey, to kill us in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, except thou make thy ſelf altogether a Prince over us?</hi> verſe 14. <hi>Moreover thou haſt not brought us into a Land that floweth with Milk and Honey, or given us Inheritance of Fields and Vineyards: wilt thou put out the eyes of men? We will not come up.</hi> Hereby you ſee that they aimed at the Supream Power.</p>
            <p>Now. what was the fair Vizard, that they put upon ſo foul a Face? Firſt they pretend to be great Enemies to Ambition. They ſaid unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, ye take too much upon you; Why lift you up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:31161:7"/>2. They cry up the People.</p>
            <p>They are an Holy People, <hi>all the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every one of them, and the Lord is among them, Wherefore then liſt ye up your ſelves above the Con: gregation of the Lord:</hi> The Preſumption of their own Holineſs, brought them to Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Affection of the Prieſthood, an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that none ſhould take to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was <hi>Aaron, Hebrews</hi> 5. 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſeem to be very tender of the peoples ſufferings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Of what <hi>Moſes</hi> had deprived them, <hi>Thou hast brought us up out of a Land flowing with Milk and Honey, to kill us in the Wilderneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In regard of what he had diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them, <hi>Thou haſt not brought us into a Land flowing with Milk and Honey, or given us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Fields and Vineyards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They ſeem to be very zealous of the Peoples liberties. <hi>All the Congregation is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> fit to govern themſelves, let all be levelled, all be equal to the Supream Power, and none be above or under others. Here was their pretence.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:31161:8"/>4. Conſider what was their way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It was cloſe and ſubtile, the <hi>Kohathites</hi> and <hi>Reubenites</hi> being gathered near each other, had opportunity to contrive their PLOT cloſely to cheat the Multitude.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Mark their Audaciouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They ſtood or roſe up in a daring manner, affronting <hi>Moſes</hi> to his Face.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They gathered themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> they banded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and came ſtrongly armed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſpake too ſaucily to them. <hi>Ye take too much upon you; why lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They charge them ſhameleſly for taking too much upon them; whereas they took no more than God had given them; And for lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up themſelves above the Congregation, when God had lifted them up to it. Yea <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was very backward to take a Commiſſion from God, and after he had it, complains of his Burden, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. 11. as deſiring to be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it. Again, they tax them for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31161:8"/> them out of a Land, flowing with Milk and Honey, <hi>viz.</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> wherein their Infants were murthered, and themſelves cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly enſlaved. And charged them for not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a Land flowing with Milk and Honey: Whereas it was their Murmuring and Unbelief that kept them out of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſhut them up in the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>Now conſider the Remedy <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Courſe he took, and there ye may ſee.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he ſhewed his utter Deteſtation of this Wickedneſs. <hi>When Moſes heard this, he fell on his Face,</hi> as abhorring ſo foul a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He makes a ſolemn Appeal to the righteous God, <hi>v.</hi> 5. He ſpake unto <hi>Korah</hi> and all his Company, ſaying, <hi>even to morrow the Lord will ſhew who are his, and who is holy, by cauſing him to come near unto him, even him who he hath choſen will he cauſe to come near unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:31161:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He Summon's <hi>Korah</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to the higheſt Judicature. <hi>This do; take the Cenſers, Korah and his Company, and put fire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and put Incenſe in them before the Lord to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: And it ſhall be, that the man whom the Lord will chuſe, he ſhall be holy,</hi> verſes 6, 7. As if he had ſaid, ye reject mine Authority, but I am content to plead this cauſe with you before the Judge of the whole world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He doth unmask them, <hi>verſes. 8, 9, 10. Seemeth it a ſmall thing to you, that the God of Iſrael hath ſeperated you from the Congregation of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to bring you near unto himſelf, to do the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Tabernacle of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And he hath brought thee near to him, and all thy Brethren, the Sons of</hi> Levi <hi>with thee, and ſeek ye the Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood alſo? For which cauſe both thou and all thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany are gathered together against the Lord: And what is</hi> Aaron <hi>that ye murmur againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:31161:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He ſends for <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> to give an account of their Action: and upon their refuſal to come up, he is full of Holy Indignation againſt their wickedneſs, and ſaid unto the Lord, <hi>verſe 15. Reſpect not thou their Offering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> He pleads his own integrity, <hi>I have not taken away one Aſs from them, neither have I hurt one of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He prays for the People whom God threatened to deſtroy upon a ſudden, for ſiding with theſe Rebels, <hi>v.</hi> 22. And then exhorts the people to withdraw from the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> leſt they be conſumed in their ſins. And then makes a Declaration to them; <hi>Hereby ye ſhall know that the Lord hath ſent me to do all theſe works; For I have not done them of mine own mind. If theſe men die the common death of all men, or if they be viſited after the Viſitation of all men, then the Lord hath not ſent me,</hi> verſe 28, 29.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:31161:10"/>
            <p>Now the Succeſs of this courſe in reſpect of the Rebels was very dreadful. One part of them the Earth opened it's Mouth, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up quick; and the other part of them was conſumed with Fire, even thoſe Two Hundred and Fifty Men that preſumed to offer Incenſe.</p>
            <p>Now in Reſpect of the People, the Iſſue was very ſtrange, though they had ſeen the hand of God in a ſtrange manner upon theſe Rebels, yet the People the next day murmured againſt <hi>Moſes and Aaron,</hi> ſaying, <hi>ye have killed the People of the Lord,</hi> Verſe 41. Whereupon the Lords Wrath was provoked, and the Plague began, and the Lord ſmote 14000 of them, though <hi>Aaron</hi> made all poſſible ſpeed to get between the dead and the living, to make aconement.</p>
            <p>Here are many things to be noted by way of obſervation.</p>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:31161:10"/>
               <head>Obſervation I.</head>
               <p>That the Churches of Chriſt in this world are ſubject to many troubles. So Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf foretold <hi>John 16. In the world ye ſhall have Tribulation:</hi> The Church in the World is like a Ship on the Sea, and it is nothing ſtrange, to ſee it toſſed with Winds and Waves: Chriſt's Ships [his Church and paſſengers] have in their Sailing more than ordinary ſtorms, <hi>Lament. 1. 12. Behold and ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſorrow be like my ſorrow,</hi> (ſaith the Church) <hi>wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me, in the day of his fierce Anger.</hi> The Ship in its nature is a tumbling and rolling thing, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving too and fro, and by its conſtitution or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for motion. The Church triumphant is landed, and is above motion, but the Church militant is afflicted and toſſed with Winds and Waves, Storms and Tempeſts. How many States and Common-Wealths are up and down, now green and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and anon in their cadency like May-Flowers?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31161:11"/> God doth many times Roll them like Bowls in an Alley: Pride, Exceſs, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Injuſtice, and abounding Iniquity, do put a Biaſs on the Bowl, that it tumbleth over and over, and God with the touch of his foot (as I may ſo ſpeak) turns the Bowl out of his place. Read the Hiſtory of the Church, and ye ſhall find that the Church for one good day of Eaſe, Peace and Reſt, hath had ten or twenty troubleſome days of War, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, Diviſion, Plots and Conſpiracies. Read the Hiſtory of the Judges, and of the perſecuting and Chriſtian Emperours, and ye ſhall ſee what viciſſitudes the Church had: It was ſometimes up and ſometimes down; they had Eaſe and Court, and favour but a ſhort time with the godly Emperours.</p>
               <p>It is true; Chriſt ſeems ſometimes to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep, and this much ſhakes his Childrens Faith, he lies as if he were aſleep, that the Paſſengers may cry aloud to him for help.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:31161:11"/>
               <p>God ſometimes would have his Church brought to a very low Ebb, and to be near unto drowning; and then he ſtands up for their deliverance; yet not ſo, but that new Storms may ariſe at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a Coaſt as they do not expect. The Church was at a low Ebb in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Males Children drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> the tasks of the men multiplied: The Lord with nineſcore Plagues cannot reſcue his People out of the hands of a Tyrant, God muſt ſtep in with imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Omnipotency to pull them out with a ſtretched out Arm in the tenth Plague.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> his word of deliverance, and Gods decree of bringing out the People, is now ready to fall to the Ground. The roaring Seas are before them, the Enemy behind them, and Mountains on every ſide: Is not the Church of God now in great danger?</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:31161:12"/>
               <p>But then ſaith <hi>Moſes, ſtand still and ſee the Salvation of God.</hi> God divides the Red Sea, for his Redeemed to paſs through, and drowns their Enemies. <hi>The Lord ſhall judg his People, and repent himſelf for his Servants:</hi> But when? <hi>When he ſeeth their strength is gone, and there is none ſhut up and left.</hi> When the Church hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hands nor feet, then God will ariſe for their help. Chriſt can Sail againſt Wind and Tide, and without Wind: He never ſinks his Bark, nor breaks his Helm, nor loſeth a Paſſenger, nor miſſeth his Harbour: though the Winds be ſtrong, and the Sea tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet the Port is ſure: For this is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of him that ſits at the Helm, <hi>Iſa. 54. 11. O thou afflicted and toſſed with Tempeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I will lay thy Stones with fair Colours, and lay thy Foundations with Saphyrs.</hi> Yea, the harbour is near. <hi>Behold I come quickly</hi> ſaith the Lord. In the greateſt ſtorm that ever fell on the Church, it could ſee the Shoar and dry Land, Let the Church remember that ſhe is in the deep, and ſo prepare for foul weather. The Church of God hath had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31161:12"/> much experience of this Truth in all ages, and happy are they that make aright improve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation II.</head>
               <p>2. That in times of vacancy and reſt, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent Spirits are apt to be working and hatching miſchief. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> was confin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Wilderneſs many years, <hi>Korah</hi> and his accomplices fell into this mutiny. When men want grace in their hearts, and buſineſs to employ themſelves about, their luſts are apt to boyl them up into ſome miſchievous attempts. When Heretical and Anti-Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Enemies are Vigilant and Active; Let us be Sober, Watch, and Pray: We have to do with Enemies that are moſt buſie, when we are leaſt Apprehenſive of Danger. Thoſe who outrun others in ſinful Activity, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Turbulency and Unquietneſs of their Spirits, as they are without peace themſelves; So they ſeek to moleſt and diſturb the peace of others. The Prophet deſcribes them to be like the troubled Sea, which cannot reſt. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31161:13"/>
               <head>Obſervation III.</head>
               <p>That Pride is the cauſe of Contention, it makes men to overvalue themſelves, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue others: Therefore the <hi>Romans</hi> paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Pride in the form of a Devil, having three Crowns upon his head, one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the Firſt was written <hi>Tranſcendo,</hi> I ſurpaſs all others, becauſe the proud man think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he exceedeth all other men. Therefore ſaith <hi>Hugo,</hi> Pride is a Vicious Haughtineſs, whereby a man deſpiſeth his inferiours, and earneſtly buſieth himſelf to rule over his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, and thoſe alſo that are above him.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Crown was written, <hi>Non obedio,</hi> I obey no others; for pride would give laws to others, but obey none himſelf.</p>
               <p>In the third was written, <hi>Perturbo,</hi> I trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all, and ſometimes the Pride of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons troubleth a whole Nation. <hi>Prov. 13. 10. Only by Pride cometh Contention;</hi> It is the great Incendiary of the World. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſheweth that when the Emperours began to favour the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31161:13"/> Chriſtians, they began to fall out and diſagree among themſelves.</p>
               <p>In the time of the ten famous Perſecutions of the Church by the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heathen <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, it is noted, that after the death of <hi>Valerian,</hi> the Church had reſt and proſperity for above forty years: In this time the Church grew exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and Chriſtians were gratious in the eyes of Emperours, and Preſidents; and many Churches were built for them, which proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity being abuſed by the Biſhops and the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and other Chriſtians unto Pride, and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſtrife and Contention; It moved the Lord to ſcourge them with another (See the tenth Perſecution) which began in the nineteenth year of the <hi>Emperour Diocleſtan,</hi> which raged very ſore, and extended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Iſland, which was then under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment of the <hi>Romans: Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> though they had a Preheminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove many others, yet the Pride of their Spirits, cauſeth them to ſwell againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:31161:14"/>
               <p>Humility of Spirit is a ſpecial means to keep the heart in peace with God, and from breaking out into irregular motions. An humble man bleſſeth God that he hath raiſed him above any others, and is not troubled that others are raiſed higher than himſelf. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> confeſſeth himſelf to be leſs than the leaſt of all God's Mercies. Some think others too high, who think themſelves not high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, Plenty, Riches, and Proſperity, do uſually puff men up with Pride, and Pride ingendereth ſtrife and contention. <hi>He that is of a Proud Heart ſtireth up Strife. Prov.</hi> 28. 25. Some men are contentious to ſhew that they are men of Spirit, <hi>Proud and Haughty Scorner is his name, who dealeth in Proud Wrath. Prov.</hi> 21. 24. Some men are violent and wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful meerly out of Pride, that others may know they are men of mettle. This is proud Wrath, as the wiſe Man termeth it.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:31161:14"/>
               <p>Ambition, Pride, and immoderate deſire of greatneſs moved <hi>Alexandria</hi> the Great to wage War with <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſia.</hi> This was the Cauſe of the Civil war between <hi>Caeſar and Pompey, Sylla and Marius, Anthony and Auguſtus.</hi> Pride hath been the cauſe of many Schiſms and Diviſions in the Church. Hence the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> ran into Schiſms and Parties, one was for <hi>Paul,</hi> another was for <hi>Apollos,</hi> a third was for <hi>Caephas,</hi> a fourth above all Miniſters and Ordinances; he is for Chriſt alone. Whence aroſe the ſtrife between <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and between <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Demetrius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> whence aroſe the ſtirs that <hi>Montanus De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius,</hi> and <hi>Arrius</hi> made in the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiphan</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Theodoret</hi> lib. 1. cap. 8. <hi>Sozom.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 18.</note> Church, whence were the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions between <hi>Paulinus</hi> and <hi>Flavianus, Lucifer and Euſebius;</hi> the <hi>Meletians</hi> and <hi>Euſtathians,</hi> all at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning good Chriſtians, and embracing true Doctrine, yet at laſt ſo divided they were, that the one Excommunicated the other; whence was the ſtrife between <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31161:15"/> the one part, and <hi>Cyril, Theophilus,</hi> and <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> of the other about the Burning of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens</hi> Books, did not all theſe contentions ſpring from Pride? whence were the contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong certain Popes and Popiſh Biſhops, was it not from Pride, was it not about the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, which ambitious Popes have proudly challenged? Humility is a low Poſtern, at which the Proud man will not ſtoop: Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is an High City, yet hath but a low Gate, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, Peace is humble, Pride quite overlooks her.</p>
               <p>The ſafeſt way to keep fire is to rake it up in Embers, and the beſt way to preſerve Peace, is in Humility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation IV.</head>
               <p>That near Neighbourhood between men of corrupt Principles and working Spirits, is very dangerous to the publick. <hi>Korah</hi> with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31161:15"/> the <hi>Kohathites,</hi> and <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> with the <hi>Reubenites,</hi> were quartered on the South ſide of the Tabernacle.</p>
               <p>This near Situation gave them opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of frequent coming together, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they had an advantage of hatching this wicked PLOT againſt <hi>MOSES</hi> and <hi>AARON.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Confederacy in Evil is ſtrong in Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. God complaineth, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 25. of the Prophets of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thus,</p>
               <p>There is a Conſpiracy of her Prophets in the midſt thereof.</p>
               <p>The Hebrew for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy is from a root, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt ligare col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligare, &amp; Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice dicitur de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum colligatione, conjurare, facere li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam.</note> or word which ſignifies to bind, to tye together, as <hi>Jeremiah 51. 63. Iſaiah</hi> 49. 16. and metaphorically is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the minds of men combining together,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31161:16"/> as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 31. It is ſaid, <hi>that Ahitophel is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Conſpirators with Abſalom: Backſherim in Conſpirationibus,</hi> his mind with others of his Aſſociates, was United in a Conſpiracy againſt <hi>David:</hi> So 2 <hi>Kings 12. 20. Jehoaſh</hi> his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants aroſe and made a Conſpiracy: It is in the Original, they conſpired a Conſpiracy; they were all of one heart and mind, and it was to kill their Maſter. Being fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and dwelling together, they had the more opportunities of meeting together to Plot the Deſtruction of their Maſter. So the evil Prophets had a Conſpiracy; they met in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they conſulted and agreed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Prophecy the ſame things, that none ſhould Prophecy otherwiſe: they made a Conſpiracy againſt the true Prophets, and thoſe that were truly Religious, oppoſing God and Godlineſs. Ye may read how they ſet themſelves againſt <hi>Jeremiah. Chap.</hi> 26. 8. and ſtired up the Princes and People againſt him. <hi>verſe</hi> 13. How they Prophecied the ſame things, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 23. 17. Such was the Counſel of <hi>Trent,</hi> a meer Conſpiracy, did
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31161:16"/> they not agree together, that whoever Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt their Canons and Articles ſhould be Anathematized; did they not ſtir up the Princes and Powers of the world, to puniſh thoſe they Judged Schiſmaticks and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation V.</head>
               <p>That outward bleſſings beſtowed upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil men, do commonly become ſnares to themſelves, and ſometimes hurtful and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the Common-Wealth. Theſe Conſpiratours were Princeſs of the Aſſembly, famous in the Congregation, men of Name, or Renown. Their dignity put them upon this mutiny with hope of ſucceſs. Poyſon given in Wine worketh ſtrongly, Sin meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with outward advantages is the more miſchievous, when evil men come to places of Eminency, they vent the Corruptions that lay hid in them before; they make Progreſs in Wickedneſs and nothing reſtrains them, we are ready to think that great men that have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31161:17"/> had good Education, are well natured, will prove admirable Inſtruments of God's glory, and the publick good; but we deceive our ſelves in ſome, when they come to high and publick places, their evil natures do appear, and they grow worſe and worſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nero</hi> at firſt for five years carried himſelf well, like a Lamb, but he was a Lion, and his Lioniſh diſpoſition ſhewed it ſelf to the full.</p>
               <p>Theſe Princes of the Aſſembly perverted the end, for which they were ordained of God, and ſet up by men, in <hi>Micahs</hi> days, the heads of the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> abhorred Judgment, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted all equity; They build up <hi>Sion</hi> with Blood, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Iniquity: and for their ſins and ſakes was <hi>Sion</hi> Plowed as a Field, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> made heaps.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:31161:17"/>
               <p>The <hi>Venetian</hi> Hiſtory informs us, that in a time when the Common-Wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> was much afflicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baimonti Tepulo,</hi> who iſſued from a noble family, but bearing a Deviliſh hatred to his Country, with divers others of the ſame quality and means, conſpired againſt it, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the common people being in pay with the Conſpirators, who in the midſt of a horrible tempeſt intermingled with hail and rain, the air being filled with Thunder and Lightening, ran armed to the Pallace, which they aſſailed, having filled the large Market-Place of St. <hi>Marks</hi> with armed men.</p>
               <p>The whole City was quickly in Armes, and there was a ſore Fight; the Fight ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not till ſuch time as the Senate getting the upperhand, the Conſpirators were beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en back from the Palace. <hi>Baimonti</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his own houſe through the <hi>Mercers</hi> Street, a woman forth of a Window, threw a Mortar on his head, with which blow he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31161:18"/> fell half dead to the Ground, and was ſlain out right by thoſe who perſued him, who preſently returned to the Pallace. Some of the Conſpirators which were Patricians by birth, being taken on the Dice-Bridge, were by the command of the Prince forthwith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed; whereupon that place hath ever ſince born the Name of <hi>Mal-pas.</hi> And to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the memory of theſe wretches, it was decreed in all places to deface the Arms of <hi>Baimonti</hi> and his Complices; their houſes were razed to the Ground, and all their Goods confiſcated, a Penſion was given to the Woman and her <hi>Heirs,</hi> who with the blow of the Mortar ſtayed <hi>Baimonti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had beſieged the Caſtle of <hi>Roxburgh,</hi> which was ready to be ſurrendred unto him, the Queen came to the Camp in great haſte un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King, ſignifying that there was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy begun againſt him, The King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon raiſed the Siege, and returned home.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:31161:18"/>
               <p>Now <hi>Walter Stuart,</hi> Earl of <hi>Athol</hi> and head of the Conſpiracy, pretending a right to the Crown, procured his Nephew <hi>Robert Stuart,</hi> and his Couſin <hi>Robert Graham</hi> to ſlay the King. Hereupon the ſaid <hi>Robert Stuart</hi> and <hi>Graham,</hi> came one Evening to the Black Friars in <hi>Perth,</hi> where the King then lay, and by Licence of the Porters, coming into the houſe, ran up into the Gallery before the Kings Chamber-Door, minding to have ſtaid there till one of the Kings Servants, who was Privy to their wicked purpoſe, ſhould come to give them entrance into the Chamber; but before the coming of this Traitor, another of the Kings Servants, named <hi>Walter Staunton,</hi> came forth of the Chamber-Door to have fetched Wine for the King, who ſeeing theſe two Traitors ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there at the Door, either of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a long Sword girded to him, he ſtept back and cryed Treaſon, but e're he could get within the door to make it faſt, they leap'd upon him, and flew him there.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:31161:19"/>
               <p>Mean while a young Virgin, named <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharine Douglas,</hi> that was afterward Married to <hi>Allexander Lovel</hi> of <hi>Bolunni,</hi> got to the Door and ſhut it; but becauſe the Bar was away that ſhould have faſtened it, ſhe thruſt her arm in the place where the Bar ſhould have been put, and being young, and her bones tender, her armes was chruſhed aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the door broke up by force. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they entred the Chamber, ſlaying ſuch of the Servants as made defence, and then the King himſelf with many cruel and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wounds. The Queen alſo was hurt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſave the King her Husband. <hi>Patrick Dunbar,</hi> Brother to <hi>George</hi> late Earl of <hi>March,</hi> was left for dead on the floor, by reaſon of ſuch Wounds as he received in the Kings defence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation VI.</head>
               <p>That Pride, Envy, and Malice, will make men inſolent in their carriage toward thoſe that are of greateſt worth, and dignity and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31161:19"/> deſert. Was ever Nation more obliged to a man, than this People to <hi>Moſes?</hi> Did any man carry himſelf with more Meekneſs than he did, and more Integrity? But no Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Worth can exempt him from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of thoſe whom Pride and Envy hath made more brutiſh than the Beaſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Ye ſee how ſawcily theſe men ſpeak to <hi>Moſes and Aaron; Ye take too much upon you, Why lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord? How stubbornly did Thomas Becket</hi> oppoſe King <hi>Henry</hi> the Second? How Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently did <hi>Bonner and Gardner,</hi> two Popiſh Biſhops, behave themſelves againſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth? In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, how ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly did the Popiſh Doctors behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in refuſing to diſpute with the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, according to that order which was preſcribed, and refuſing to ſet the Royal Crown upon her Head? No wonder that thoſe who maintain Errours and Lies, audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and obſtinately againſt the truth of God, do all ſhew themſelves Preſumptious and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31161:20"/> Inſolent againſt Princes and Magiſtrates. St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls them, 2 <hi>Pet. 20. Preſumptuous and Self-willed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Preſumptuous, the word is in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Men of daring and audacious Spirits, impudently bold or preſumptuous. Hereticks, what they want of Truth in their Doctrines, they labour to make up with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency and boldneſs, not only againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours, but alſo againſt Governours, whom God hath ſet in his own place, eſpecially when they have got ſtrength on their ſide. Again ſaith <hi>St. Peter,</hi> they are <hi>Self-willed</hi> and ſtubborn, and refractory <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Men that will pleaſe themſelves, and have their own will and way, in deſpite of Authority. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and falſe Teachers, proud, envious, and malicious men, out of ſelf-will Pride, and frowardneſs, behave themſelves audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and impudently againſt their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and will go their own way, becauſe they will.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:31161:20"/>
               <p>In the firſt Reformation in <hi>England,</hi> under K. <hi>Edward the</hi> VI, the Popiſh Prelates and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy (the State having before diſcarded the Pope) did eaſily joyn with the Proteſtants, though not in their Opinions, yet in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service of the Church, and had not the Pope ſoon after been reſtored by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> to his former Authority, in all Probability that Faction long ſince had been ended; but after the Readmiſſion of the Pope, and his having Liberty to tamper with his Party at pleaſure, in the Second Reformation by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> not a <hi>Popiſh Biſhop</hi> could be perſwaded to come to our Church: And this practiſe hath been continued by the greateſt part of the <hi>Recuſants,</hi> their <hi>Followers,</hi> to this Day; notwithſtanding our Service be, in it ſelf, leſs offenſive to them, and in no part oppoſite to any point of their Creed, than that in King <hi>Edwards</hi> was. Thus it pleaſed their Politick Governours, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and perpetuate the Remains of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by this utter Breach and Alienation, inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting them, not only the reading of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Books, and repairing to their Churches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:31161:21"/> but alſo to joyn with them in any Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, by whomſoever, or how lawful ſoever performed, thereby kindling in them, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream hatred and deteſtation of their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation VII.</head>
               <p>That thoſe that know not how to govern themſelves, and are much more unfit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern others, are apt to deſpite Government, and labour to deſtroy it. This ye ſee here in the Examples of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> Looſe and Licentious Spirits would have none above them that ſhould have Power to reſtrain them. Luſt and Corruption are Irregularities, which abhor to come under Order. St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, <hi>v. 8. They defile the fleſh, deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi> They deſpiſe not only Men in Authority, but Dominion and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelf, cannot endure to be in Subjection to Lawful Anthority. And it may be obſerved,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31161:21"/> that both St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude,</hi> do joyn this ſin immediately to that Sin of Uncleanneſs, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to imply, that when men are given over to Licentious Walking after the fleſh, in the Luſt of Uncleanneſs, it is no wonder if they be ready to ſhake off due Subjection to the Civil Magiſtrate; and deſire to be freed from all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrait of good Laws and good Orders eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Common-wealth, that they may run on in their deſolute and diſorderly Courſes: Doth it not ſeem a Light Matter to Men of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Spirits</hi> to deſpiſe Government, and to tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon Laws? What elſe did Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> III. when he trode upon the Neck of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa,</hi> who was his Lord and Prince, abuſing the Sacred Scripture alſo, and turning it into a by-word of reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Soveraign, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lion and the Adder, the young Lion and the Adder ſhalt thou trample under feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:31161:22"/>
               <p>How did Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> III. deſpiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Dominion, when he Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> VI. with his Feet, and with his Foot ſtruck the Crown from his Head again? or Pope <hi>Adrian,</hi> that made the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> IV. ſtand barefoot a long time at his Gate in cold Weather?</p>
               <p>What is it but to deſpiſe Government, to depoſe Kings from their Thrones (if they croſs the Popes Will) and to diſcharge their Subjects from their Duty and Allegiance? Is it not a point of Anti-Chriſtian and High Contempt of Government, when a Pope ſhall expect, that the Emperor, his Lord and Prince ſhould hold his Stirrop, and then chide him for not hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it at the right ſide? The Apoſtle goeth on, and having ſhewed the Root of this Contempt of Government, <hi>viz. Preſumption and Self-will,</hi> he ſheweth ſome Fruits of it alſo: They are not afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities: The words in the Original are very weighty, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they tremble not to blaſpheme <hi>Glories;</hi> they tremble not; whereby he imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31161:22"/> that this is a Sin to be trembled at, <hi>viz.</hi> This Reproaching of Men, placed in Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Dignity, and that Men ſhew themſelves to be given over to a ſtrange height of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when they are not afraid to open their Mouths in reproachful Terms againſt ſuch: Then it is called <hi>Blaſpheming,</hi> becauſe Princes are called <hi>Gods,</hi> and are in the place of God here on Earth, God having communicated unto them ſome part of his Authority and Command over their Brethren by his word, as by a Commiſſion dated in the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And in that reſpect their Perſons are in a manner <hi>Sacred,</hi> and it is a petty blaſphemy to reproach them. The Apoſtle calls them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Glories,</hi> and ſo one tranſlates it, <hi>gloria praecel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes,</hi> Men eminent in Glory: And <hi>Beza,</hi> tho he tranſlates it, <hi>Dignitates</hi> (as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> alſo) yet in his notes he doth Paraphraze thus; <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta Majeſtate preditos,</hi> men endued with emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent majeſty. This ſhews what great things may be attributed to Princes and Rulers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flattery; ſo that we do not exceed the bounds which the word of God hath ſet.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31161:23"/> 
                  <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy ſecret thought, Eccl.</hi> 10. This is one ſtrong argument that the Lord doth Reign throughout the Earth, who though he doth ſometimes permit the corruptions of men to break out into diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet he doth ſo far over-rule them, as to preſerye ſome order in the Societies of men. We have cauſe to bleſs God, that though our Government hath ſuffered ſo many convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our days, yet he hath not ſuffered it to be utterly confounded. If we look upon men we are apt to complain of many things, but if we look up to God, we have cauſe to thankful that things are no worſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation VIII.</head>
               <p>It is no new thing for men of looſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to cry down Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, as theſe men would down with both at once. Thoſe men that would level us in Church and State, do not act without a Precedent. <hi>Korah</hi> and his company have ſhewed them the way. And I know not any thing doth croſs
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31161:23"/> Satan more in his deſign than a good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and a faithful Miniſtry; and therefore Satan labours, firſt to corrupt them, which if he cannot do, then to diſparrage them, and alienate the People from them. What is <hi>Korah</hi>'s Plea? Firſt, the People are holy all and every one; and then they are the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then here is the inference Firſt, then no need of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, they need not the Government of a man that have the Lord among them to govern them.</p>
               <p>2. They are an holy People, they know how to govern themſelves, they need not a Magiſtrate to keep them in order. But tho it be granted, that they are outwardly Holy, as being dedicated to God, and ſeperated from all Nations in the World; yet many of them were inwardly and really unholy, and generally they were a ſtiff-necked Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, more fit to be governed rather than left without Government.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:31161:24"/>
               <p>I ſuppoſe that our Enemies of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will not uſe altogether <hi>Korah</hi>'s Plea, they will not plead that all the People are Holy. But they go another way: The Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power (ſay they) is originally in the People, and why would they ſuffer any one ſingle Perſon to rule over them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> Should it be granted, that the power at the firſt was originally in the People, yet to inveſt the body of the People with the whole Power, what doth this ſavour of but Frenzy, Anarchy, and Madneſs, and would ſoon turn to the ruine of that People that ſhould make the tryal of it, and run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of ſo woful an experiment. Many Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories inform us, how the multitude have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been deſirous of change in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Livy</hi> makes mention of the Citizens of <hi>Capua,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Livy,</hi> Decad. 3. lib. 3.</note> gathered together in a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous manner, would needs depoſe the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and being weary of their Government, agreed to put them to death. But <hi>Pacupius</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:31161:24"/> 
                  <hi>Calavius</hi> the head Magiſtrate, being willing to ſave them, when they had paſſed ſentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of them, to have him Executed, bad them firſt in his ſtead to chuſe a good and righteous Senatour. At the firſt they were all ſilent, not knowing how to find a better: After, when ſome odd fellow of the crew, paſt all ſhame and reverence, ſeemed to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate one to ſucceed; by and by they grew to loud words and great outcries; ſome ſaid flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they kenw not the man, others laid heinous things to his charge, ſome ſaid he was of a baſe beggarly condition; others objected hsi trade and way of living: Thus they grew more and more vehement upon the propoſals of a ſecond and third to their choice. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they bethought themſelves, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of what they had done already, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much they failed, and were to ſeek upon every new Election; and ſo at length they were content to keep their old Senators ſtill. Juſt ſo it is with the many-headed mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as changeable, unconſtant, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable as the weather, never at any certainty,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31161:25"/> diſcontented with the preſent Government, which if changed for another, they would like no better, weary of preſent things, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting change and alteration; either they ſerve baſely, or rule proudly.</p>
               <p>As for liberty, that is the mean between them both, they have neither the skill to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe with reaſon, nor the grace to entertain in any proportionable meaſure, <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Wat. Ralegh</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the world.</note> as one ſaith. But what ſay our Church Levellers, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are all holy, what need there be any one to teach them? they can teach themſelves; the Church are all Saints, they all know the Lord, from the greateſt to the leaſt; what need is there then of any ſuch thing as the miniſterial Office, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 11. They have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God an Unction, or <hi>an anointing which teacheth them: and need not that any man ſhould teach them, 1 John</hi> 2. 27.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:31161:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> By Unction and Anointing is meant the Spirit and his Graces, ſo called, becauſe they are the Unction wherewith Chriſt and his Members are Anointed. Now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from hence, that the Miniſtry and the Ordinances are not neceſſary, but only the immediate teachings of the Spirit, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion never intended by the Spirit of God. Firſt, becauſe this would be contrary to his own Inſtitutions and Commands, and ſo make God to contradict himſelf: For God hath ſet up the Miniſtry, to teach, edify, and perfect Saints, he hath commanded them to Preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon. God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits us to deſpiſe Prophecying. He threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens Damnation to ſuch as ſhall neglect to hear the Goſpel Preached. To what end hath God appointed and commanded theſe things, if his mind be, that we ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately taught of God by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf makes this evident to be his meaning, 1 <hi>John 5. 13. Theſe things have I written unto you that believe on the Name of</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:31161:26"/> 
                  <hi>God.</hi> If they had been all immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> it had been abſurd for <hi>John</hi> to write unto them. But becauſe the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God doth teach by the Word mediately, therefore he writeth to them. God's Courts are his School, his ordinance are his books, by which he teacheth Men: And they that will be taught of God, muſt come to his School, and wait upon his Ordinances. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Miniſtry is to continue in the Church, <hi>till we all meet together in the Unity of Faith, and of the Knowledg of the Son of God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Stature of the Fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> The Miniſtry is to continue till we all meet in the Unity of Faith, in the Univerſal Meeting, when Chriſt ſhall appear in Glory, when we ſhall have an uniform Faith and Knowledg of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="observation">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:31161:26"/>
               <head>Obſervation IX.</head>
               <p>That thoſe that are the greateſt Deceivers of the people, do often pretend moſt Zeal for the Peoples Liberty: So we ſee here in <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his Company, St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3. of falſe Teachers, that through Covetouſneſs by feigned Words they make Merchandize of thoſe whom they ſeduce. Doth not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture among divers kinds of Merchandize in the Ware-houſe of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Souls of men? <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 19. Hereticks for Gain by feigned Words do ſell the Souls of Men to the Devil; by fair pretences they draw Men into damnable Hereſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Pernitious Practiſes, and into the way of Deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="observation">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:31161:27"/>
               <head>Obſervation X.</head>
               <p>That it is uſual with evil Men, to draw falſe Concluſions from true Premiſes. What was the ground <hi>Korah</hi> went upon: That all the Lord's People were Holy, every one of them. This is true according to Scripture, in a Senſe, externally holy, as a people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Lord to be their God. But what was the Concluſion they drew from hence, it was, that therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> took too much upon them, and that there was no need of Magiſtracy or Miniſtry. Take heed of ſudden Entertaining any New Doctrine though it ſeem to be countenanced by ſome Scripture miſapplyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="observation">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:31161:27"/>
               <head>Obſervation XI.</head>
               <p>That true Zeal doth oppoſe great Sins with great Deteſtation. This mutiny tended to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe two great Ordinances of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and Miniſtry, and to bring confuſion into the Church and Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to provoke the Wrath of God againſt them: And therefore <hi>Moſes,</hi> though the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Man upon Earth, yet he was far from cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and neutrality, in this reſpect he was full of Zeal, he falls upon his Face in Deteſtation of ſo foul a Rebellion, and was very wrath with them, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. True Zeal is proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Object. The greater the Sin is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which it is ſet, the more it is ſtirred; it is fervent as the Cauſe requireth; it is governed by true prudence or diſcretion, and proceeds with caution. A true Chriſtian uſeth Zeal as a skilful Rider doth his Horſe, making uſe of the mettle of his Horſe, ſuitable to the Uſe he hath of him. True Zeal mindeth the Cauſe, and according to the Importance of that, riſeth or falleth as the Tide, which followeth the courſe of the Moon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="observation">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:31161:28"/>
               <head>Obſervation XII.</head>
               <p>That it is true Wiſdom to undertake ſuch a Cauſe, and ſo to manage it, that whatſoever oppoſition may ariſe, a man may confidently and ſafely appeal to the righteous God. So it was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> he had undertaken an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Work, and he had managed it in an extraordinary way; yet ſuch was his carriage in it, that he approveth himſelf to God: And then if men did offend him, ſcorn and reſiſt him; here was his comfort, that his witneſs was in Heaven; though Men did condemn him yet God did juſtify him. Carnal Wiſdom thinks it beſt for men to engage in ſuch a Cauſe, and ſo to carry themſelves, that men may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with them; but it is cold comfort to a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the bar, that ſome ignorant perſons ſtanding by ſhall acquit him, and the Judge on the Bench ſhall condemn him: A good cauſe and an evil Conſcience are ſo unſuitably match'd, that ſome ſleight occaſion of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is enough to divorce them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="observation">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:31161:28"/>
               <head>Obſervation XIII.</head>
               <p>That evil Men are apt falſely to object things againſt their Betters, which may truly be retorted upon themſelves. Theſe Men ſay to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Ye take too much upon you, which Moſes</hi> reſtores unto them, <hi>v. 7. ye take too much upon you ye Sons of Levi,</hi> and juſtly accuſeth them for medling with things too high for them, which the Lord had never called them to, 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 18. 17, 18. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaith unto <hi>Elijah,</hi> Art thou he that troubleſt Iſrael? The Prophet retorteth this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, becauſe of his Abominations. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> charge Chriſts Diſciples for tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Traditions of the Elders: To whom Chriſt anſwereth, <hi>why do ye alſo transgreſs the Commandments of God by your Traditions?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="observation">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:31161:29"/>
               <head>Obſervation XIV.</head>
               <p>That evil Men pretending only to quarrel with men, do many times riſe up againſt God. Theſe Mutineers pretended to riſe up againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> but <hi>Moſes</hi> tells them, that they are riſen up againſt God, That they were gathered together againſt the Lord. <hi>What is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron that ye murmur againſt him?</hi> When by the Providence of God, Men are placed in the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and ingaged in it, and act faithfully in their places: Thoſe that band againſt them, do band againſt the God of Heaven, denying his Prerogative, whoſe Right it is to pull down one and ſet up another: Therefore when <hi>Men</hi> riſe up againſt ſuch, the Lord vindicates his own Authority, and exalts his own Name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="observation">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:31161:29"/>
               <head>Obſervation XV.</head>
               <p>That undervaluing of Gods Mercies makes Men unthankful for them, and diſcontented at their preſent Condition: <hi>Moſes ſaid unto Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, ſeemeth it a ſmall thing to you, that the God of Iſrael-hath ſeparated you from the Congregation of Iſrael, to bring you near to himſelf, to do the Service of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the Congregation, to miniſter unto them? And he hath brought thee near to himſelf, and all thy Brethren, the Sons of Levi with thee, and ſeek ye the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood alſo?</hi> When great Mercies are undervalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by evil Men, God hath little Thanks, and Men have little Content.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="observation">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:31161:30"/>
               <head>Obſervation XVI.</head>
               <p>That Evil and Unthankful <hi>Men</hi> are ſoon apt to forget thoſe <hi>Miſeries</hi> out of which the Lord hath delivered them. Theſe men <hi>v.</hi> 13. call <hi>Egypt</hi> a Land, flowing with <hi>Milk</hi> and <hi>Honey:</hi> They ſpeak not of the cruel Bondage they were kept in, that rigorous Servitude that made them weary of their Lives. Now they talk as if God and <hi>Moſes</hi> had done nothing for them, but deprived them of many comforts they had there. How many men do ſoon forget thoſe dangers, miſeries and ſtraits out of which God hath delivered them? Such forgetfulneſs is diſpleaſing to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="observation">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:31161:30"/>
               <head>Obſervation XVII.</head>
               <p>That thoſe that undertake to maintain a bad Cauſe; who want Strength of Argument to maintain it, they will ſtrengthen it with great words, they will talk confidently and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily before the people, who are apt to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more with words than matter.</p>
               <p>So here theſe Men talk confidently to <hi>Moſes,</hi> who being called to come up to the place of Judicature, ſay, <hi>we will not come up: Wilt thou make thy ſelf altogether a Prince over us? Wilt thou put out the eyes of theſe Men?</hi> Unleſs thou wilt ſay the people have loſt their Eyes, they may ſee thou art guilty of wronging the Multitude. Falſe Teachers are ſaid <hi>to ſpeak ſwelling Words, full of vanity, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 19. Hereticks love to ſpeak in a lofty ſtrain, to amaze the ignorant: With what great ſwelling Words do the Popiſh Hereticks ſet forth the Pope's uſurped <hi>Supremacy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and the glory of their Church? How do they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31161:31"/> talk of <hi>Antiquity, Univerſality, perpetual Succeſſion, Inſalibility, glorious Miracles,</hi> ſuch as Chriſt and his Apoſtles never wrought? How do their words ſwell in extolling their Popes Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over Councils, making his words ſpoken in his Chair as Divine Oracles, as if they had iſſued out of the Throne of Chriſt? let us then put a great difference between great ſwelling words of Vanity, and ſolid and ſubſtantial truths.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation XVIII.</head>
               <p>That Malice in accuſing thoſe that are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, doth uſually catch at ſhadows to enforce an accuſation againſt the innocent. <hi>Moſes,</hi> had brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into the Wilderneſs, but with no intent to keep them there. Now <hi>Korah</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany charge <hi>Moſes,</hi> for bringing them out of a land flowing with Milk and Honey, to kill them in the Wilderneſs. Now this was but a ſhadow, it was their own ſin that detained them there, and kept them out of the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> So <hi>Doeg</hi> to humour <hi>Saul,</hi> malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31161:31"/> accuſed <hi>Ahimelech</hi> the Prieſt of Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with <hi>David</hi> againſt the King, becauſe he enquired of the Lord for him, gave him bread, and the Sword of <hi>Goliah.</hi> This ſhould teach us not to be too haſty in entertaining falſe reports upon men of worth and eminency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation XIX.</head>
               <p>Here ye may obſerve Gods ſeverity againſt the Rebels and Traitours, that roſe up againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Enemies to Magiſtracy and Miniſtry: The ground clave aſunder that was under them, and the earth opened her mouth, and ſwallowed them up, and their houſes, and all the men that appertained unto <hi>Korah,</hi> and all their goods: they and all that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to them, went down alive into the pit, and the earth cloſed upon them, and they periſhed from among the Congregation. And all <hi>Iſrael</hi> that were round about them, fled at the cry of them; for they ſaid leſt the earth ſwallow us up alſo. And there came out a fire from the Lord, and conſumed the two hundred and fifty men that offered Incenſe.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:31161:32"/>
               <p>God's puniſhments on Traitors are of three ſorts, <hi>External, Internal Eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1ſt- <hi>External,</hi> either when he doth it by ordinary means extraordinarily ſtirred up. The Servants of <hi>Amon</hi> conſpired againſt him, and ſlew the King in his own houſe, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the land ſlew all them that had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt King <hi>Amon 2 Reg.</hi> 21, 23, 24. Or by means which man cannot uſe, as <hi>Miriam</hi> was ſmitten with Leproſie for murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 12. 1. This puniſhment was memorable both for the ſuddenneſs and ſoreneſs of it; wherefore it is after-ſaid, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what the Lord thy God did to</hi> Miriam <hi>in the way after that ye came forth out of Egypt, Deut. 24. 9. Abſalom</hi> was hanged by the hair alive upon an Oak and ſmitten by <hi>Joab,</hi> and here I have ſhewn you how ſeverely God dwelt with <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his company.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:31161:32"/>
               <p>2dly, <hi>Internal,</hi> in Conſcience, ſuch as will not obey for Conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5, nor ſubmit for the Lords ſake, and deprived of a good Conſcience, which is a continual feaſt.</p>
               <p>3dly. <hi>Eternal</hi> puniſhment, ſedition is one of the works of the Fleſh, a ſin that keeps a man out of Heaven without Repentance, <hi>Gal. 5. 19, 20. They that reſist this ordinance of God, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation, Rom.</hi> 13. 2.</p>
               <p>As theſe men are odious to God, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are they odious to men. No man will truſt a Traitor. When <hi>Viriatus</hi> his Souldiers had ſlain him, thinking to pleaſe <hi>Scipio,</hi> and get a reward (in that <hi>Viriatus</hi> had ſtirred up <hi>Spain</hi> for fourteen years together againſt <hi>Rome)</hi> they had nothing but this anſwer for cold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>Nunquam placuiſſet Imperatorem a ſuis Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus interfici,</hi> that it never pleaſed the Romans to have an Emperor killed by his Souldiers. <hi>Selymus</hi> the Grand Seignior, having hired his Phiſitian to poiſon his father <hi>Bajazet,</hi> he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward cut off his head, leſt he would be hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:31161:33"/> to do the like againſt him. <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> made uſe of Traytors to bring his matters to paſs, but hated them extreamly afterward. When <hi>Laſthenes</hi> that had betrayed the City of <hi>Olynthum</hi> to him, complained that the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were called by the <hi>Macedonians, Proditores,</hi> he anſwered, the <hi>Macedonians</hi> are plain rude fellows, calling every thing by its proper name, calling a Spade a Spade. The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> having taken <hi>Rhegium,</hi> about three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Traytors were taken alive, who preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after their coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> were by the Commanders of the war brought into the Market-places, where they were whipped, and in the end their heads were ſtruck off, after the manner of their Country.</p>
               <p>The Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> IV. in his war againſt <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> corrupted three of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with promiſe of great reward if they would betray <hi>Philip</hi> into his hands, by making him flee through falſe fear, they did it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the promiſed reward.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:31161:33"/>
               <p>The Emperour had provided for them a mighty Maſs of Counterfeit Money, which he gave them: they returning, afterward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that they were deceived with Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Coyn; the Emperour anſwered, <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terinum aurum, pro adulterino opere,</hi> that counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeit Coyn was a worthy reward for counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Knaves, falſe Coyn for a falſe Work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Justian</hi> of <hi>Genoa</hi> having betrayed <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> upon condition, that he ſhould make him King thereof under him, he made him King thereof, and Crowned him moſt Royally, but within three days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cut off his head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pauſanias</hi> having received five hundred Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of Gold of <hi>Xerxes</hi> to betray <hi>Sparta, Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus,</hi> his Father, when he fled into a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to ſave himſelf, cauſed the Gates of the Temple to be walled up, and ſo he died of hunger, whoſe body his Mother cauſed to be caſt to the Dogs, and would not bury it.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:31161:34"/>
               <p>All men hate Traitors, <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, men are affected towards Traitors, whom they are driven of neceſſity to uſe, as men that uſe the poyſon of a Viper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they willingly uſe the poyſon, but hate the poyſonful Creature. So many that willingly make uſe of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, do hate the Traitor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="observation">
               <head>Obſervation XX.</head>
               <p>That evil men make an ill uſe of beholding God's judgments upon others: inſtead of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves under the hand of God, they are apt to fall foul upon others, <hi>verſe 41. On the morrow all the Congregation of Iſrael murmured againſt Moſes and againſt Aaron, ſaying, ye have killed people of the Lord.</hi> The judgment of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Korah</hi> and his Company was before then eyes, and yet on the morrow they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended again, what they had ſeen God to do, they impute to <hi>Moſes and Aaron.</hi> Themſelves had been ſaved by the Prayers of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:31161:34"/> now thus they requite them. They repine more at the loſs of a few than at the ſaving of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and many thouſands others. Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring in Scripture is called by the Name of <hi>Rebellion.</hi> After this murmuring of the people againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in the next Chapter, <hi>v.</hi> 10. The Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> bring <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod again before the Teſtimony to be kept for a Token againſt the <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt God, to murmur is to have a heart riſing againſt the Lord. A general Diſcontent and Murmuring in a Nation is uſually the Forerunner of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Murmuring is the root of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt God. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, That Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers do enter into Judgment with God.</p>
               <p>Conſider the Evil of Murmuring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is a great piece of Folly to murmur at any of Gods Diſpenſations with us, and God at one time or other, will ſhew ſuch Men their Folly. It is great Vanity to think we can redreſs any Evils by our own Wiſdom, <hi>for who can make ſtraight that which God hath made crooked,</hi> Eccl. 7. 13. Moreover by murmuring, ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deprive
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:31161:35"/> your ſelves of the comfort and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all your Enjoyments. If it be a pleaſant thing to be thankful, then on the contrary, it is an unpleaſant thing to be murmuring. And let me add, if you let looſe your Tongues to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur againſt Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and any of Gods Inſtruments, God hath an Ear to hear all your Murmurings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 6, 7. The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> but ſay they to the people. <hi>In the Morning ye ſhall ſee the Glory of the Lord, for that he heareth your mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings against the Lord. And what are we, that ye murmur againſt us,</hi> verſe 8. Ye murmur not ſo much againſt us, as againſt the Lord. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us a <hi>Caveat,</hi> to take heed of murmuring, <hi>Neither murmur ye, as ſome of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo murmured, and were deſtroyed of the deſtroyer.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> no ſooner brake out into this Sin after the death of <hi>Korah</hi> and his Confederates, but God ſent the Plague among them, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Fourteen thouſand and ſeven hundred, beſide them that dyed in the matter of <hi>Korah.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:31161:35"/>
               <p>And now I wiſh that that Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29. laſt may be made good this day; <hi>That all that erred in ſpirit ſhall come to underſtanding, and they that murmured ſhall learn Doctrine.</hi> To mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at Gods Providences, is very prejudicial to us, <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a great Feaſt for his Nobles and Friends, the day fell out to be very wet, that nothing could be done to the honour of that meeting; <hi>Caeſar</hi> being greatly diſpleaſed, willed all them that had bows, to ſhoot up their Arrows at <hi>Jupiter</hi> (then their chief God) in defiance of him for that rainy weather; which they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. But the Arrows fell ſhort of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and falling upon their own heads, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them were ſorely wounded; ſo by our murmuring againſt our Rulers, or againſt any of Gods Providences, we hurt not him at all, but they will light on our own heads, and wound us dangerouſly. Let us all ſtudy peace, and live peaceably, and labour to make up thoſe unhappy breaches that are among us.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:31161:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the Life of <hi>Agricola</hi> his Father-in-Law, deſcribing the Faſhions, Chivilry and Reſolutions of the <hi>Britains</hi> in that time obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this alſo, that they were then drawn into divers petty Factions, and the greateſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that the <hi>Romans</hi> had againſt that our War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Nation, was, That they had no <hi>Common Council;</hi> They did not conſult together, but each City fought againſt their Neighbours, <hi>(&amp; ita dum ſinguli pugnant,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>univerſi vincun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur)</hi> whilſt one by one fighteth, all are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: And it is much to be feared, That the <hi>Romans</hi> are again ready to ſet foot into our Land; they expect to get ground by our home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Factions and Diviſions; ſo that the Pope hath now hopes of a great Harveſt in <hi>England:</hi> And how can we think the Church of <hi>England</hi> can ſtand (ſaith one) when there be Sizers and Conſizers, ſo many Cuters and Carvers of her Members? Moreover let us all be content with that Condition in the World, which God hath allotted us, keeping our ſelves within our due Bounds.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:31161:36"/>
               <p>There's a notable Story for this in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Pyrrhus.</hi> One <hi>Cineas</hi> adviſeth him to deſiſt from the Wars with the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that the <hi>Romans</hi> are Good Men of War, and if it pleaſe the Gods we do overcome them what Benefit ſhall we have of that Victory? <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> anſwered him, we ſhall then ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer all <hi>Italy,</hi> with eaſe. <hi>Cineas</hi> replyed, it is probable it may be as your Highneſs ſpeaketh, but when we have won <hi>Italy,</hi> will our Wars be then at an end? If the Gods were pleaſed, <hi>ſaid Pyrrhus,</hi> That the Victory were atchieved then might we afterwards go into <hi>Africa</hi> and ſo to <hi>Carthage:</hi> But when we have gotten all into our hands, ſaid <hi>Cineas,</hi> What ſhall we do then? Then <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> laughing ſaid, we will then be quiet, and take our eaſe, and eat, drink and be merry every day. To whom <hi>Cineas</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſaying, and what hindreth us now from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing merry together, and at quiet, ſithe we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that preſently without further coſt, travel and trouble, which we ſhould ſeek for abroad,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:31161:37"/> with ſo much danger and Bloodſhedding. So how quietly and comfortably might men live together, could they be content with their preſent Condition, did not the corruption of their hearts ſwell them into Diſcontent, Pride and Faction; Making them to tranſgreſs the Bounds, wherein God hath placed them. Now the Lord of Peace give us Peace, all ways, by all means.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:31161:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
